Klaus E. Rieckhoff fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Klaus E. Rieckhoff fonds
1960 - 1993
F-220
Q104445445
13 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Rieckhoff, Klaus E.
Klaus Ekkehard Rieckhoff is Professor Emeritus in the Department of Physics at Simon Fraser University (SFU). He helped shape the department and the university through his active involvement in the governance of SFU, through his contributions to science and his devotion to teaching, as well as his involvement in the larger community.
Born in Weimar, Germany, Rieckhoff experienced life under both the Nazi and Communist regimes before escaping from the Soviet-occupied zone in 1947. Shortly after, he left for the western zones where he worked in various factories in Munich until he was accepted at the University of Karlsruhe where he studied mathematics and physics (1947-1949). He was accepted for one of 40 places in physics and mathematics from a pool of 400 applicants after an entrance examination administered to 160 of the applicants. In 1949, he left the university while continuing to work as a clerk in the actuarial department of a life insurance company (1948-1951). In December 1949, he married Marianne Neder with whom he has three children, Bernhard Andreas, Claudia Angela, and Cornelia Andrea.
Rieckhoff immigrated to Canada in 1952. Upon his arrival to Vancouver, B.C., he held various jobs as a dock worker (1952), sawmill worker (1953), and television technician (1953-1957) before earning his B.Sc., M.Sc., and Ph.D at the University of British Columbia.
In 1965, Rieckhoff joined SFU as a charter faculty member and immersed himself in its life. He is regarded as a vital force in the Department of Physics, a department he helped to create and nurture. From 1966-1967, he was Acting Dean of Science, and from 1972-1976, he was Associate Dean of Graduate Studies. He has authored and co-authored more than 60 papers in the areas of spectroscopy and chemical physics, earning international recognition for his work. From 1976-1977, he worked at the IBM Research Lab in San Jose, California as Visiting Scientist. In 1987, he was a Visiting Professor at the universities of Puerto Rico (Mayaguez, U.S.A.), Queensland (Brisbane, Australia), and Bayreuth (Germany).
Rieckhoff's passion for critical inquiry is reflected in his multiple appointments, participation, and election to a number of faculty, departmental, and university committees. As a founding member of Senate, he supported the inclusion of undergraduate representation. He served on the Senate for 17 years and on the Board of Governors for 11 years, earning him the distinction of being one of the longest-serving members on both bodies. In recognition of his contributions to the governance and administration of SFU, the university named the Senate Chamber in his honour in 1982. Although the space has been renovated, a plaque remains in place. In 1998, SFU awarded him a Doctor of Laws, honoris causa.
published
Full
Revised
Title is based on the name of of the fonds creator.
Fonds consists of records arising from Klaus Rieckhoff's teaching and research activities as well as records made and received by Rieckhoff as an elected member of the SFU Senate, Board of Governors, and various faculty, departmental, and university committees. Records include correspondence, memos, notes, publications, reports, lists, minutes, and evaluations.
The material was arranged by the archivist into series based on the academic and professional activities of Klaus Rieckhoff.
Science and technology
The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by Klaus Rieckhoff in 2006.
All accessions have been processed as of April 2012. No further accruals are expected.
For other material relating to Klaus Rieckhoff see the finding aids to F-33, Board of Governors fonds, F-70, Allan B. Cunningham fonds, F-84, Senate fonds, F-91, Ceremonies and Events Office fonds, F-223, Hugh Johnston fonds, and F-247, SFU Archives Reference and Display Materials collection.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the reference archivist for more details.
File and item lists are avaiable.
- Communications inquiry records, 1971 - 1978; F-220-1; 2 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the President's Committee of Inquiry into the Department of Communication Studies, a committee appointment by President Pauline Jewett to investigate ongoing conflicts within the department since its emergence as its own discipline at SFU. Originally, communication studies was a discipline within the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, which took in three programs from Education: Kinesiology, Communications, and Fine and Performing Arts.
  Series includes correspondence, memos, notes, pamphlets, class lists, reports, course descriptions, and evaluations made and received by Klaus Rieckhoff while he was a member of the Committee of Inquiry.
  Committee of Inquiry into Department of Communication Studies; School of Communication
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  - Communications inquiry, vol. 1, 1971 - 1978; F-220-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - small 220-2)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Communications inquiry, vol. 2, 1977 - 1978; F-220-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - small 220-2)
- Correspondence, 1973 - 1992; F-220-2; 4 cm of textual records
  Series consists of personal and professional correspondence between Klaus Rieckhoff and various friends, colleagues, and peers. Records consist primarily of correspondence but also include copies of memos and handwritten drafts of correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1977 - 1978; F-220-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - small 220-2)
    Restricted in whole
  - Correspondence, 1978 - 1979; F-220-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - small 220-2)
  - Correspondence, 1978; F-220-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - small 220-2)
    Open
  - Correspondence, 1973 - 1992; F-220-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - small 220-2)
- Faculty, departmental, and university committee records, 1983 - 1984; F-220-3; 2 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to issues discussed in Senate and Board of Governors committee meetings. Includes correspondence made and received by Rieckhoff, memos, notes, minutes, and reports. For a list of committees of which Rieckhoff was a member, see access points.
  Senate; President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities; Board of Governors; Senate Graduate Studies Committee
  - SFU Senate and Board of Governors committee work, 1983 - 1984; F-220-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - small 220-1)
- Publications, 1960 - 1983; F-220-4; 5 cm of textual records
  Series consists primarily of articles authored and co-authored by Klaus Rieckhoff that focused on chemical physics and that were published in scientific journals and as reports. See access points for a list of journal titles.
  Individual publications have been registered as items. See item list for titles.
  Canadian Journal of Physics; Physics Review; Physics Letters; Journal of Chemical Physics; Canadian Journal of Spectroscopy; IBM; Applied Physics Letters; Physical Review Letters; Science; The Review of Scientific Instruments; Chemical Physics; Helvetica Chimica Acta; Journal of Physical Chemistry; Canadian Journal of Chemistry; Optics Communication; Spectroscopy Letters; Chemical Physics Letters; National Academy of Sciences; Spectrochimica Acta; Molecular Physics; Journal of Molecular Spectroscopy
  The records are open with no restrictions.
  - Publications, vol. 1, 1960 - 1971; F-220-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Phosphorescence and Fluorescence of Phthalocyanines." The Journal of Chemical Physics, Vol. 55, No. 8, 4131-4140., October 1971; F-220-4-0-0-1-1 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Polarizability of Molecules in Excited Electronic States." The Journal of Chemical Physics, Vol. 55, No. 7, 3317-3327., October 1971; F-220-4-0-0-1-2 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Induced Bireference as a Method for Studying the Electronic Transitions and Polarizability of Molecules in Excited Electronic States.", April 1970; F-220-4-0-0-1-3 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Laser-induced dielectric breakdown and mechanical damage in silicate glasses." Canadian Journal of Physics, Vol. 48, No. 10, 1178-1191., 1970; F-220-4-0-0-1-4 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Laser Induced Underwater Sparks." Applied Physics Letters, Vol. 13, No. 8, 282-284., October 1968; F-220-4-0-0-1-5 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Optical Anisotropy of an Excited Electronic State." Physical Review Letters, Vol. 20, No. 7, 309-310., February 1968; F-220-4-0-0-1-6 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Laser-Induced Photoconductivity in Silicate Glasses by Multiphoton Excitation, A Precursor of Dielectric Breakdown and Mechanical Damage." Canadian Journal of Physics, Vol. 45, 3781-3791., 1967; F-220-4-0-0-1-7 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Laser-Induced Luminescence and Dissociation in Biphenyl." The Journal of Chemical Physics, Vol. 44, No. 12, 4492-4497., June 1966; F-220-4-0-0-1-8 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Self- Induced Divergence of CW Laser Beams in Liquids - A New Nonlinear Effect in the Propagation of Light." Applied Physics Letters, Vol. 9, No. 2, 87-88., July 1966; F-220-4-0-0-1-9 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Polarization Effects in the Two-Photon Excitation of Anthracene Fluorescence." The Journal of Chemical Physics, Vol. 42, No. 12, 4164-4169., June 1965; F-220-4-0-0-1-10 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Polarization of Anthracene Fluorescence by One and Two Photon Excitation." Physics Letters, Vol. 15, No. 3, 230-231., April 1965; F-220-4-0-0-1-11 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Optical Second-Harmonic Generation in Crystalline Amino Acids." Science, Vol. 147, 610-611., February 1965; F-220-4-0-0-1-12 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Stimulated Brillouin Scattering in Liquids." Physical Review Letters, Vol. 13, No. 11, 334-336., September 1964; F-220-4-0-0-1-13 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Double-Photon Excitation of Organic Molecules in Dilute Solution." The Journal of Chemical Physics, Vol. 39, No. 5, 1347-1348., September 1963; F-220-4-0-0-1-14 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Double Photon Excitation in Organic Crystals." Physical Review Letters, Vol. 10, No. 2, 43-45., January 1963; F-220-4-0-0-1-15 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Optical Faraday Rotation Studies of Paramagnetic Resonance in Neodymium Ethylsulphate." Canadian Journal of Physics, Vol. 41, 33-45., 1963; F-220-4-0-0-1-16 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "X-Band Resonant Cavity for Optical Studies at Liquid Helium Temperatures." The Review of Scientific Instruments, Vol. 33, No. 12, 1393-1396., December 1962; F-220-4-0-0-1-17 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Spin-lattice and Cross-relaxation Effects in Neodymium Ethylsulphate at Liquid He Temperatures." Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on L.T. Physics, London., 1962; F-220-4-0-0-1-18 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Spin Lattice Relaxation in Neodymium Ethylsulphate at Liquid Helium Temperatures." Canadian Journal of Physics, Vol. 38, 604-615., 1960; F-220-4-0-0-1-19 (Archival box - small 220-1)
  - Publications, vol. 2, 1972 - 1980; F-220-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "On the Resonance Enhanced Raman Bands of Tetracyanoethylene Anion Dimer." Canadian Journal of Spectroscopy, Vol. 25, No. 6, 148-150., 1980; F-220-4-0-0-2-1 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Platinum Phthalocyanine Symmetry and Singlet-Triplet Energy Transfer from Electronic and Vibronic Shpol'skii Spectra." Chemical Physics, 36, 423-436., 1979; F-220-4-0-0-2-2 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Spectra of Organic Molecules in Thin Films." Helvetica Chimica Acta, 61, Fasc. 3, 960-977., 1978; F-220-4-0-0-2-3 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Spectroscopic Studies on the Conformations of Electron Donor-Acceptor Complexes of Tetracyanoethylene." The Journal of Physical Chemistry, Vol. 82, No. 18, 2005-2012., 1978; F-220-4-0-0-2-4 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Resonance Raman in platinum phthalocyanine." Canadian Journal of Chemistry, Vol. 56, No. 7, 976-984., 1978; F-220-4-0-0-2-5 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Optical Properties of Arachidate Monolayers By Integrated Optical Techniques." Optics Communications, Vol. 24, No. 1, 146-148., 1978; F-220-4-0-0-2-6 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "On the Temperature Dependence of Multiple Charge-Transfer Bands in pi-pi Electron Donor-Acceptor Complexes." The Journal of Physical Chemistry, Vol. 81, No. 8, 809-810., 1977; F-220-4-0-0-2-7 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Determination of Equilibrium Constants for Electron Donor-Acceptor Complexes by Resonance Raman Spectroscopy." The Journal of Physical Chemistry, Vol. 81, No. 15, 1489-1492., May 1977; F-220-4-0-0-2-8 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Spin-Orbit Effects in Metalphthalocyanines." Chemical Physics, Vol. 19, No. 1, 25-33., January 1977; F-220-4-0-0-2-9 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Revised Assignment of the Raman Active Fundamental Vibrations of Tetracyanoethylene." Spectroscopy Letters, 10(2), 99-104., January 1977; F-220-4-0-0-2-10 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Model Theory of Resonance Raman Excitation Profiles in Electron Donor/Acceptor Complexes." Chemical Physics Letters, Vol. 45, No. 2, 250-254., January 1977; F-220-4-0-0-2-11 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Photoionic Dissociation of Electron Donor/Acceptor Complexes of Tetracyanoethylene in Solution." Chemical Physics Letters, Vol. 44, No. 3, 482-483., December 1976; F-220-4-0-0-2-12 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Activation energy barrier for intersystem crossing in platinum phthalocyanine." Canadian Journal of Physics, Vol. 54, No. 6, 633-637., 1976; F-220-4-0-0-2-13 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Low Energy Raman Bands in TCNE and Its EDA Complexes." Chemical Physics Letters, Vol. 39, No. 3, 521-524., May 1976; F-220-4-0-0-2-14 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Raman resonance of electron donor/acceptor complexes (resonance Raman spectroscopy/resonance Raman vibronic theory/electron donor-acceptor charge transfer)." Proceedings of The National Academy of Sciences, Vol. 72, No. 11, 4196-4199., November 1975; F-220-4-0-0-2-15 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Preresonance Raman Intensity Studies in Electron Donor/Acceptor Complexes of Tetracyanoethylene." Chemical Physics Letters, Vol. 30, No. 3, 480-484., February 1975; F-220-4-0-0-2-16 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Frequency Shifts and Intensity Changes in the Raman Spectra of Liquid Mixtures of TCNE with Aromatic Electron Donors." Chemical Physics Letters, Vol. 23, No. 1, 5-8., November 1973; F-220-4-0-0-2-17 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Reducing the incidence of cracks and solute microcrystals in frozen luminescent solutions." Spectrochimica Acta, Vol. 29A, 1673-1674., 1973; F-220-4-0-0-2-18 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Dynamics of the triplet state of phthalocyanine complexes of the platinum metals in zero field." The Journal of Chemical Physics, Vol. 58, No. 12, 5726-5734., June 1973; F-220-4-0-0-2-19 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Effects of Thermal Lensing in Glass Lasers." Canadian Journal of Physics, Vol. 50, No. 14, 1656-1658., 1972; F-220-4-0-0-2-20 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Relaxation Mechanisms from Excited Singlet States and the Effect of Spin-Orbit Coupling." Chemical Physics Letters, Vol. 13, No. 6, 604-607., April 1972; F-220-4-0-0-2-21 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Molecular Fluorescence from High Vibrational Levels of Excited Electronic States." Physical Review Letters, Vol. 28, No. 5, 261-263., January 1972; F-220-4-0-0-2-22 (Archival box - small 220-1)
  - Publications, vol. 3, 1981 - 1983; F-220-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - [List of publications authored and co-authored by K.E. Rieckhoff - revised Feb. 25, 1993], February 1993; F-220-4-0-0-3-1 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Hole-burning in the amorphous and in the crystalline local environment of an n-hexadecane Shpol'skii matrix." Chemical Physics Letters, Vol. 190, No. 1.2, 67-71., February 1992; F-220-4-0-0-3-2 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Electronic spectra and photochemical transformation of tertiary butylphthalocyanine in Shpol'skii matrices." Spectrochimica Acta, Vol. 47A, No. 8, 1023-1040., 1991; F-220-4-0-0-3-3 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Photochemical transformation of metal-free phthalocyanine in a Shpol'skii matrix." Spectrochimica Acta, Vol. 46A, No. 11, 1601-1613., 1990; F-220-4-0-0-3-4 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Electronic spectra and Zeeman effect of ruthenium phthalocyanine in Shpol'skii matrices." Molecular Physics, Vol. 68, No. 2, 341-357., 1989; F-220-4-0-0-3-5 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Double fluorescence lifetimes of metal-free phthalocyanine in a mixed-solvent Shpol'skii matrix at 4.2K." Molecular Physics, Vol. 67, No. 6, 1439-1443., 1989; F-220-4-0-0-3-6 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Low-lying activated states of chloroiridium phthalocyanine aggregates in glassy solution at low temperatures." Canadian Journal of Physics, Vol. 66, 86-92., 1988; F-220-4-0-0-3-7 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Zeeman effect of the platinum phthalocyanine n-pi* phosphorescences." Molecular Physics, Vol. 62, No. 3, 541-558., 1987; F-220-4-0-0-3-8 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "The first excited states of platinum phthalocyanine in magnetic fields." Molecular Physics, Vol. 59, No. 2, 355-369., 1986; F-220-4-0-0-3-9 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "The Dynamics of Palladium Phthalocyanine Excited States in Magnetic Fields at Low Temperatures." Chemical Physics, 102, 193-203., 1986; F-220-4-0-0-3-10 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Zeeman Study of the Phosphorescent State of Palladium Phthalocyanine in Shpol'skii Matrices." Chemical Physics, 95, 123-133., 1985; F-220-4-0-0-3-11 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Thermostable sites of palladium phthalocyanine in Shpol'skii matrices of mixed solvents." Canadian Journal of Chemistry, Vol. 62, 2264-2272., 1984; F-220-4-0-0-3-12 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Resonance Raman, fluorescence, and phosphorescence of palladium phthalocyanine in Shpol'skii matrices." Journal of Chemical Physics, Vol. 80, No. 9, 4051-4064., May 1984; F-220-4-0-0-3-13 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "A New Assignment of the Raman Spectrum of Tetracyanoethylene Anion Dimer, (TCNE-)2." Chemical Physics Letters, Vol. 99, No. 5, 6, 512-514., August 1983; F-220-4-0-0-3-14 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Shpol'skii effect and vibronic spectra of the phthalocyanines." The Journal of Chemical Physics, Vol. 77, No. 7, 3424-3441., October 1982; F-220-4-0-0-3-15 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "Valence Force Field Analysis of Tetracyanoethylene." Journal of Molecular Spectroscopy, Vol. 95, 1-8., 1982; F-220-4-0-0-3-16 (Archival box - small 220-1)
    - "New Singlets in the Phthalocyanines." The Journal of Physical Chemistry, Vol. 85, No. 22, 3322-3326., 1981; F-220-4-0-0-3-17 (Archival box - small 220-1)